A Guide to the David Rockefeller papers, Photographic collections, Numbered Albums FA1316
Rockefeller Archive Center
David Rockefeller papers, Photographic collections, Numbered albums
1916-2016
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller, Peggy
Reed, Joseph
FA1316
95.50 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Materials related to living members of the Rockefeller family are restricted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The albums in this collection primarily contain images of David Rockefeller (DR) with his family, friends, personal office staff, or Chase Manhattan Bank colleagues during his travels throughout the globe. A second common album theme is DR with Peggy, his wife, at one of their homes: Hudson Pines in Pocantico Hills, New York; their townhouse on East 65th Street in Manhattan; Ringing Point in Seal Harbor, Maine; or Colombier, on St. Bart's, in the Caribbean. However, there are also hundreds of images from DR's childhood and from his service in Europe during World War II.
The timeframe of the albums ranges from as early as DR's infancy, approximately starting in 1916, and goes throughout his lifetime, with the last album created in 2016. Of particular note are the albums from David's youth, including images he took while on family vacations. During his undergraduate years (mid-1930s), he traveled in Europe with his camera in hand. Then during World War II, he was stationed with the U.S. Army in France and took images while on leave in several countries.
By the 1950s, DR traveled internationally on behalf of his employer, Chase Manhattan Bank. The albums of his visits to several African nations are among the earliest images documenting those activities. His interest in Latin America is evident as early as the 1950s in this collection. After his retirement in 1980, DR continued to represent Chase Bank as a member of its International Advisory Committee (IAC), which led to further travel and albums from many of those trips. In the latter part of the 20th century, DR was described as an unofficial diplomat for the United States. The images found throughout this collection that depict his numerous meetings with heads of state attest to this informal but significant capacity and the lasting connections he made in all of his roles.
For each box, the contents of the album within are broadly described, along with details on the number of images and approximate date. Most images are prints, although there is a large aggregate of slides from mid-century. All images are in color unless otherwise noted.
Lastly, the albums with material related to living members of the Rockefeller family are restricted from research access during each individual's lifetime. Therefore, approximately 45 percent of the collection of albums remains restricted at this time even though there is description available in this finding aid. The archival staff will conduct periodic reviews to open additional albums and update this finding aid.
Arrangement
Arranged as received. These albums are in no discernible order, although some portions of the finding aid reflect semi-alphabetical runs of travel destinations. Sometimes trips to the same location over a range of years are in consecutive boxes, but that is not the general rule. At times, similar formats are grouped in a range of boxes. For example, most of the slides are located between Box 279 and Box 292, although a few are elsewhere in this collection. Albums on specific destinations (such as Seal Harbor, Maine) or events (such as DR's 100th birthday celebrations) appear throughout the collection.
Biographical / Historical
David Rockefeller was born on June 12, 1915, in New York City, the youngest of the six children of Abby Aldrich and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. He attended Lincoln School of Columbia University's Teachers College in New York and graduated from Harvard University in 1936 with a B.S. degree in economics. After post-graduate study at Harvard and the London School of Economics, he received a Ph.D. degree in economics from the University of Chicago in 1940. His doctoral thesis, "Unused Resources and Economic Waste," was published that year by the University of Chicago Press.
On September 7, 1940, David married Margaret (Peggy) McGrath. Together they raised two sons and four daughters. They maintained homes in Manhattan; Pocantico Hills, New York; Seal Harbor, Maine; and St. Bart's in the Caribbean.
From 1940 to 1941, David served as secretary to New York Mayor Fiorello H. LaGuardia. He then served as assistant regional director of the U.S. Office of Defense, Health and Welfare Service (1941-1942) before enlisting as a private in the U.S. Army in May 1942. He entered Officer Candidate School in 1943 and was discharged as a captain in 1945. During World War II he served in North Africa and France, where for seven months he was an assistant military attaché in Paris. He was awarded the U.S. Legion of Merit, the U.S. Army Commendation Ribbon, and the French Legion of Honor.
Business Career After the war, David began a career in banking. He joined the Chase National Bank as an assistant manager in the foreign department in 1946. He was appointed an assistant cashier in 1947, second vice president in 1948, and vice president in 1949. From 1950 to 1952, he was responsible for the supervision of the bank's business in Latin America. In 1952 he was named a senior vice president with responsibility for supervising the economic research department and customer relations in metropolitan New York.
When Chase National and the Bank of the Manhattan Company merged in 1955, David was appointed an executive vice president in charge of the bank development department. In 1957 he became vice chair of the board of directors with responsibility for the administrative and planning functions of the bank as a whole. He became president of the bank and chair of the executive committee of the board of directors in 1961, and in 1969 he became chair of the board and chief executive officer. David retired from the bank in 1981. During his career with Chase Manhattan, David gained a worldwide reputation as a leading banker and spokesperson for the business community. He spearheaded the bank's expansion both internationally and throughout metropolitan New York and helped the bank play a significant role as a corporate citizen.
Philanthropy and Public Service In addition to his work with Chase Manhattan, David was a leader in many public and private projects, reflecting his wide-ranging interests in international, governmental, civic, and cultural affairs and his belief in collaboration between the public and private sectors. In 1940 he became a member of the board of trustees of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. A decade later he succeeded his father as chair of the board, serving in that capacity for 25 years (1950-1975). He led the transformation of the research institute into a biomedical graduate university, which was renamed The Rockefeller University in 1965. Along with his brothers, David established the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (RBF) in 1940. He also helped found the Rockefeller Family Fund in 1967 and joined with his brothers in a number of other philanthropic, economic development, and investment initiatives.
Among the other family philanthropic enterprises he served was the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), which his mother had helped create. Following her death in 1948, David took her seat on the board of directors, serving several times as its chair. He also was a life trustee of the University of Chicago (which his grandfather helped establish) and an honorary trustee of International House (New York), established by his father.
Locally, David helped create the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Association (D-LMA) in 1958 and served as its chair until 1975. Its planning proposals aided the redevelopment of lower Manhattan and led to the creation of the World Trade Center. He also played a major role in the development of the Morningside Heights neighborhood on the Upper West Side of Manhattan as president (1947-1957) and then chair (1957-1965) of Morningside Heights, Inc. As chair of the New York City Partnership (1979-1988), he was a leader in organizing the city's business sector to work with government on such major public issues as economic growth, summer jobs for students, improving the city's schools, and housing development.
In the realm of international affairs, David established and worked with a variety of organizations that furthered his belief in "constructive engagement" and the promotion of dialogue among business professionals and government officials across national borders. In 1949 he became a director of the Council on Foreign Relations, an educational institution where leaders from the field of scholarship and the public and private sectors meet periodically to expand their perspectives on foreign affairs; he served as the council's chair from 1970 to 1985. He also attended the annual Bilderberg meetings, established by Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands, from their inception in 1954. In 1973, he helped found the Trilateral Commission, an organization designed to promote understanding and cooperation among the nations of North America, Western Europe, and Japan.
In the 1960s Rockefeller helped organize both the Council of the Americas and the Center for Inter-American Relations, which worked to maximize private enterprise contributions and cultural and intellectual exchanges in the development of Latin America. These were reorganized as the Americas Society in 1982. He also helped to establish the David Rockefeller Center for Latin American Studies at Harvard University, which opened in 1994.
Rockefeller Center In the 1980s and 1990s, David played an active role in the financing and ownership of the Manhattan landmark his father had built, Rockefeller Center. In March 1982 he became chair of Rockefeller Center, Inc., which was renamed Rockefeller Group, Inc. (RGI) the following year. He oversaw efforts to beautify, diversify and unify Rockefeller Center, which included capital improvements to modernize the facility. In January 1985, RGI bought the 12 acres of land underneath the buildings from Columbia University for $400 million, the highest per-acre price ever paid for a parcel of urban real estate. The resulting new company, Rockefeller Center Properties, Inc. (RCPI), held a public offering of its stock that raised $1.3 billion, which RCPI lent to RGI in exchange for a mortgage on the land and buildings of Rockefeller Center.
In September 1989, David and his associates sold 80 percent of RGI to the Mitsubishi Estate Corporation of Japan for $1.373 billion. Even though the Rockefeller family retained ownership of 20 percent of Rockefeller Center, the sale of a controlling interest in such a prominent landmark was controversial. But the sale came at the end of a real estate boom in Manhattan and on the eve of a worldwide real estate recession; in the changed marketplace, Rockefeller Center went bankrupt in May 1995.
Disappointed by the bankruptcy of the landmark bearing the family name, David assembled a group of investors that bought Rockefeller Center in March 1996. Rockefeller insisted that his partners agree to hold onto the property for five years before considering a sale. During that time, as the real estate recession ended, the Center's management refurbished the facility and made it more attractive. In December 2000, David and his partners agreed to sell Rockefeller Center to a group of investors led by Jerry Speyer for $1.85 billion, thus ending the Rockefeller family's ownership of Rockefeller Center.
David Rockefeller died on March 20, 2017, at his home in Pocantico Hills, New York, at the age of 101. In May 2018, in accordance with David's wishes, Christie's auction house held sales of most of David and Peggy's extensive art collection. The sales raised more than $860 million for the benefit of 10 nonprofit and philanthropic organizations.
Photographs
- Jeddah, Saudi Arabia Trip, 1984 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  DR trip to Jeddah on behalf of Chase Manahttan Bank's International Advisory Committee. He met with Abdul Aziz Al-Sulaiman, chair of ROLACO, a trading and contracting company.
  File Plan
  8 images.
- Williamsburg, VA Trip, 2006 (Box 2)
  DR visit to Colonial Williamsburg, VA, with family members. DR met with Colin Campbell, director of Colonial Williamsburg, and toured the site.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Material related to living members of the Rockefeller family is restricted.
  14 images.
- Hudson Pines Family Album, 1955, Black-and-white images. (Box 3)
  DR and PR with their children at Hudson Pines, their home in Pocantico Hills, New York. Images of horseback riding, playing with pets, posing in the garden, posing in the living room, posing at the front staircase.
  31 images.
- St. Bart's Trip, 1978 (Box 4)
  DR and PR trip to their home, Colombier, on St. Bart's in the Caribbean. Guests included Henry Kissinger, Nancy Kissinger, Robert Douglass, Linda Douglass, Winston Lord, and Bette Bao Lord.
  15 images.
- Chase Manhattan Bank Art Program, Tenth Anniversary Celebration, 1969 April 17; Black-and-white images and clippings. (Box 5)
  Chase Manhattan Bank celebrated the tenth anniversary of its art program by hosting a dinner for the artists whose works appeared in their buildings. DR and PR hosted. Alfred Barr Jr. attended. Artists included Isamu Noguchi, Marisol, and Robert Indiana. Images and clippings.
  51 images.
- Dartmouth V International Conference, Party at Pocantico Playhouse, New York, 1969 January; Black-and-white images. (Box 6)
  DR hosted at party at the Playhouse for the attendees of the Dartmouth V International Conference, which was held in Rye, New York. Topics included cultural and scientific exchanges, arms controls, the United Nations, Vietnam, and the Middle East. Paticipants were from the United States and the Soviet Union. Happy Rockefeller attended the party.
  43 images
- Estate Fountain Valley Golf Course, St. Croix, 1970 (Box 7)
  Promotional images for golfing and sightseeing at Estate Fountain Valley, St. Croix, U.S. Virgin Islands.
  45 images.
- FLF Hudson Pines, Celebration of Francois de Rose's 90th Birthday, 2000 May (Box 8)
  DR's friend from his years in the Army during World War II. Francois de Rose and Ivonne de Rose visited DR at Hudson Pines and the 65th Street townhouse while in the United States to celebrate Mr. de Rose's 90th birthday. They also toured Rockefeller Center, Museum of Modern Art, and the Union Church at Pocantico Hills. Henry Kissinger, Nancy Kissinger, and Donald Rumsfeld were guests at the dinner celebration.
  63 images.
- Fort Worth, Texas, Reception for Lady Bird Johnson and Peggy Rockefeller, 1969 October 9; Mostly black-and-white images. (Box 9)
  Exhibition at the Amon Carter Museum in Fort Worth and reception at the Ridglea Country Club to celebrate publication of "Wild Flowers of the United States, Volume Three: Texas." Attendees included DR and PR, former President Lyndon Johnson, Lady Bird Johnson, Ruth Carter Stevenson, and Van Cliburn.
  28 images.
- George River Trip, Quebec, Canada, 1970 September; Some black-and-white images. (Box 10)
  DR and PR on a hunting and fishing trip along the George River. Visit to local community school and church.
  57 images.
- "Happy Memories," Compilation Album of DR and PR, 1977-1997; Some black-and-white images. (Box 11)
  Album compiled by family friends Gustavo and Patricia Cisneros of several visits and travels with DR and PR.
  39 images.
- Maine Vacation, August 1970, 1970 August; Color is faded in some images. (Box 12)
  DR and PR vacation with friends in Maine. Visit to Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Garden in Seal Harbor. Sailing and hiking.
- Matinicus Island, Maine Cruise, 1993 April 21 (Box 13)
  DR and PR on board Augustin Edwards' yacht, the Gloriana, sailing with friends around Matinicus Island off the coast of Maine.
  19 images.
- Middle East Trip for Chase Manhattan Bank, 1980, 1980 January-February (Box 14)
  DR trip to 7 countries on behalf of Chase Manhattan Bank, along with Joseph Reed and Robert Douglass: Morocco, Egypt, the Sudan, Saudi Arabia, Jordan, Cyprus, and Israel. They toured historical and religious sites, markets, and the Great Pyramids. DR met with Menachem Begin and Moshe Dayan while in Israel.
  26 images.
- New York to London, Rome, and Paris Trip, 2002, 2002 March (Box 15)
  DR travels with granddaughter to London, Rome, and Paris. Visits to Salisbury Cathedral, St. Peter's Basilica and Square, Colosseum, and Forum.
- New Zealand Trip, Mini Album, 2006 February (Box 16)
  27 images
  DR sailing trip with family and friends to New Zealand. This is a subset of the photos from the larger album found in Box 17.
- New Zealand Trip, 2006 February (Box 17)
  DR sailing trip with family and friends to New Zealand.
  81 images.
- Retirement Party at Playhouse for Alfred Barr, 1967 June 22; Black-and-white images. (Box 18)
  DR and PR hosted a retirement party for Alfred Barr, director of the Museum of Modern Art, at the Playhouse in Pocantico Hills, New York. Attendees included Rene d'Harnoncourt, Nelson Rockefeller, Happy Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Blanchette Rockefeller, and Dorothy Miller.
  33 images.
- Seal Harbor, Maine, Album of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Garden, 2002 (Box 19)
  This compilation album of professional photos was a Christmas gift to DR from Gregory Hudson. The photos are of the flowers and plants at the Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Garden in Seal Harbor, Maine.
  50 images.
- St. Bart's Trip, 1983, 1983 November (Box 20)
  DR and PR trip with friends for Thanksgiving weekend to Colombier, their home on St. Bart's in the Caribbean. Sailing, hiking, wildlife.
  37 images.
- Studio Museum in Harlem, 1970 January; Black-and-white images, plus a few clippings. (Box 21)
  Chase Manhattan Bank sponsored an art show held at the Martha Jackson Gallery in Manhattan, with a benefit opening to support the Studio Museum in Harlem. The museum celebrates African American artists. The event also marked the tenth anniversary of Chase Bank's art program, so the bank pledged to buy any unsold works for its own collection.
- Andrew and Betsy Wyeth, Maine, 2008 (Box 22)
  DR visit to Southern Island, Maine, home of artist Andrew and Betsy Wyeth. Son Jamie Wyeth, also an artist, is present.
  13 images
- Bohemian Grove Encampment, Sonoma County, California, 1955; Black-and-white images. (Box 23)
  During the summer of 1955, DR attended a men's retreat at a private redwood forest campground, Bohemian Grove, in Sonoma County, California.
- La Commanderie du Bontemps de Medoc, France, 1953 May (Box 24)
  Ceremony when DR was inducted as a member of La Commanderie du Bontemps de Medoc, a renowned wine appreciation society in France.
  11 images.
- Buckle Island Garden Album, Maine, 1968 (Box 25)
  Compilation album displaying the variety of flowers and plants in the Buckle Island garden.
- Morocco Trip, Part 2, 1983, 1983 February (Box 26)
  DR and PR trip through Morocco with friends Robert Douglass, Linda Douglass, J. Richardson Dilworth, Elizabeth Dilworth. Camel rides, markets, visit to Sahara Desert sand dunes, trip across Atlas Mountains, landscapes.
  140 images.
- Akio Morita and David Rockefeller Trip to Hawaii, 1997 March (Box 27)
  DR joined Akio Morita, cofounder of the Sony Corporation, in Hawaii at a golf resort.
  28 images
- Mt. Desert Island, Maine Trip, 1995, 1995 August (Box 28)
  Family trip to property on Mt. Desert Island. Images of landscape plus family members with farm animals and landscape images.
  29 images.
- National Gallery of Art Exhibition, 1959 April; Black-and-white images. (Box 29)
  DR lent Manet's "La Brioche" to the Masterpieces of Impressionist and Post-Impressionist Painting exhibition at the National Gallery of Art in Washington, DC. Images of the museum galleries and attendees.
  16 images.
- Seal Harbor, Maine Compilation Album, 1960-1989, Some black-and-white images.; Some images are faded/blurry. (Box 30)
  DR and PR trips to Seal Harbor, Maine, with family and friends. Sailing, hiking, garden tours, berry picking. Includes winter visits, unlike most of the other compilation albums. Guests include Robert Douglass, Linda Douglass, Margaretta (Happy) Rockefeller and her family. Richard playing bagpipes on a boat.
  199 images.
- Seal Harbor, Maine Trip, 1999 (Box 31)
  23 images.
- SY Red Dragon Cruise, 2005 (Box 32)
  DR sailing, possibly on the Red Dragon, with friends and family.
  20 images.
- Syria Trip for Chase Manhattan Bank, 1977; Black-and-white images. (Box 33)
  DR trip to Syria on behalf of Chase Manhattan Bank. Meetings and tours.
- Album of the Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Garden, 1971 (Box 34)
  Small album of the flowers, plantings, and sculpture in the Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Garden in Seal Harbor, Maine.
  10 images.
- Watanabe Lunch, Tokyo, 1989, 1989 November (Box 35)
  DR visit to Tokyo on behalf of Chase Manhattan Bank included a lunch hosted by Takejiro Watanabe.
- 7 Nations Africa Trip, Chase Manhattan Bank, 1959; Mostly black-and-white images (Box 36)
  Chase Manhattan Bank trip by David Rockefeller and John Watts, sponsored by the Council on Foreign Relations and the Carnegie Corporation. Visited 7 African countries in 5 weeks (in order): Nigeria, Ghana, Belgian Congo, South Africa, Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, Kenya, and Republic of Sudan.
  16 images
- Alaska Trip, 2002 (Box 37)
  DR sailing trip from Petersburg, Alaska. Petersburg among towns visited. Rick Fleishman and Dan Walton accompanied him.
  69 images
- Amazon and Venezuela Trip, 1985; Somes images are grainy. (Box 38)
  DR and PR trip to Venezuela and and an Amazon excursion with Chase Manhattan Bank international group.
  91 images
- Arequipa, Peru Trip, 1998 (Box 39)
  DR trip to the Arequipa region of Peru to visit Cuajone Mine with staff of Southern Peru copper mining corporation.
  49 images
- Buenos Aires, Argentina Trip, 1986 January (Box 40)
  DR trip to Buenos Aires, Argentina, which was part of a longer trip for the Americas Society that included visits to Uruguay and Brazil. Argentinian Amalia de Fortabat hosted DR and appears in most of the images.
  48 images
- U.S. Army Service, Photos by David Rockefeller during World War II, 1943-1945; Black-and-white images. (Box 41)
  During World War II, DR served in the U.S. Army and was stationed in northern Africa and France. He took most of these photos in areas where he was stationed or traveling to while on leave.
  29 images
- 10 Nations Africa Trip, Chase Manhattan Bank, 1982 (Box 42)
  Trip to 10 African nations with members of DR's staff and Chase Manhattan Bank staff. Two of the ten countries visited are Ivory Coast (Cote d'Ivoire) and Nigeria. DR met with Henry Konan Bedie and Felix Houphouet Boigny, both former presidents of Cote d'Ivoire. In Nigeria, DR met with Ado Abdullahi Bayero, Emir of Kano. Hughlyn F. Fierce also joined the group.
  92 images
- Australia and Papua New Guinea Trip, Part 1, 1981; Some black-and-white images. (Box 43)
  DR and PR trip to Australia for meetings of the International Advisory Committee (IAC). Henry Kissinger also attended the meeting in Sydney. The Rockefellers then visited their properties at Orleans Farms and Oceanview Farms, and then they took boat and helicopter trips along the Kawarari River and Sepik River, Papua New Guinea.
- Australia Trip to Orleans Farms, 1964, 1964 October (Box 44)
  DR and PR trip to their property at Orleans Farms in Esperance, Western Australia. A side trip during a business trip to Australia.
  30 images
- Bahrain Trip, 1994 November (Box 45)
  DR trip to Bahrain on behalf of Chase Bank. Includes visit to Bahrain Oil Museum.